Guide to the George Clement Perkins Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Clement Perkins papers
1862-1946
1879-1915
WA MSS S-2706
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.84
(7 boxes)
The Papers consist of speeches, correspondence, financial records, photographs, scrapbooks and ephemera documenting the political life of George Clement Perkins. Speeches consist of manuscript versions in unidentified hands. Some speeches are identified within the folders; others are untitled and undated. The papers do not comprehensively document Perkins's official activities as a California legislator and governor, but focus on his political activity generally and his 1879 gubernatorial campaign. Some ephemera documents the activities of the Bohemian Club of San Francisco circa 1880. Posthumous records document Perkins's estate.
Perkins, George C. (George Clement), 1839-1923
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Vigilante Rare Books on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
George Clement Perkins, 1839-1923
George Clement Perkins was born in Kennebunkport, Maine in 1839 and died in Oakland, California in 1923. He began his career as a cabin boy on a merchant ship and quickly became successful in diverse entrepreneurial endeavors, including a steamship business. A Republican politician and businessman, he was a California State Senator (1869-1876), the 14th governor of California (1880-1883) and a United States Senator (1893-1915). He was married to Ruth A. Parker and they had several children.
Scope and Contents
The Papers consist of speeches, correspondence, financial records, photographs, scrapbooks and ephemera documenting the political life of George C. Perkins. Speeches consist of manuscript versions in unidentified hands. Some speeches are identified within the folders; others are untitled and undated. The papers do not comprehensively document Perkins's official activities as a California legislator and governor, but focus on his political activity generally and his 1879 gubernatorial campaign. Some ephemera documents the activities of the Bohemian Club of San Francisco circa 1880. Posthumous records document Perkins's estate.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Speeches, circa 1880-circa 1915. II. Correspondence and Business Papers, 1862-1946. III. Photographs, 1880-circa 1940. IV. Other Papers, 1878-1915.
Governors -- California; Legislators -- California; Legislators -- United States; Political campaigns -- California; California -- Politics and government -- 1850-1950; Photographic prints; Speeches (documents) -- California -- 1850-1950; Governors -- California -- 1850-1950; Legislators -- California -- 1850-1950; Legislators -- United States -- 1850-1950; Perkins, George C. (George Clement), 1839-1923; Bohemian Club (San Francisco, Calif.); California. Legislature
- Speeches, circa 1880-circa 1915; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. consists of manuscript versions (in unidentified hands) of speeches by George C. Perkins.
  - Speeches by Perkins, manuscripts, undated [1880s-1910s] (Box 1, Folder 1-21)
- Correspondence and Business Papers, 1862-1946; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series II consists of correspondence, financial records, invitations, and estate documents. Correspondence during Perkins's lifetime is fragmentary and relates chiefly to his social and political activity and to legal affairs, but does not comprehensively document his official duties as California legislator and governor. Correspondence and papers after 1923 relate chiefly to Perkins's estate. Financial records relate chiefly to the business of Goodall, Nelson & Perkins (later Goodall, Perkins & Co.).
  - Correspondence, 1860-1916 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Invitations, 1880-1926 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Empty envelopes, 1897-1931 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Financial records, 1862-1899 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Perkins estate records, 1916-1946 (Box 2, Folder 28-31)
- Photographs, 1880-1940; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series III includes several copies of a portrait of George C. Perkins as California governor, circa 1880. Also included are unidentified photographs, presumably of family members, possibly including George C. Perkins as a young man.
  - Portraits of George C. Perkins, including reproductions and engravings, circa 1880 (Box 3, Folder 32-38)
  - George C. Perkins and family members, including Fred K. Perkins, circa 1880- circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Members of the Assembly, 33rd Session, California Legislature, 1899
- Other Papers, 1878-1915; Series IV; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series IV consists of scrapbooks, clippings, printed ephemera, and sketches. Scrapbooks and clippings relate chiefly to Perkins's political campaigns and activity. Printed ephemera includes brochures and broadsides relating to Perkins. Sketches are pencil studies of shapes, signed "Perkins." Also included is a printed version of a speech by Charles E. Travers.
  - Twenty-Eighth Anniversary of the Corporate Society of California Pioneers, oration by Col. Charles E. Travers, printed version, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Scrapbook of gubernatorial campaign, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Scrapbook of Senate years, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Scrapbook, 1890s
  - Clippings, 1879-1915 (Box 4, Folder 43-60)
  - Clippings, 1893-1913 (Box 5, Folder 61-65)
  - Printed ephemera, 1885-1910, undated (Box 5, Folder 66-67)
  - Printed ephemera relating to the Bohemian Club, San Francisco, California, 1879-1882 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Pen Pictures of our Representative Men, by Hugh J. Mohan, E.H. Clough, John P. Cosgrave, printed versions, inscribed by the authors, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 69-70)
  - Sketches, studies of shapes, pencil, undated
- Oversize Material, 0.17; (2 boxes)
  - Engraving of George C. Perkins (Series III.), undated (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Photograph of Members of the Assembly, 33rd Session, California Legislature (Series III.), 1899 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Printed ephemera (Series IV.), 1885, undated (Box 6, Folder 73-74)
  - Sketches, studies of shapes, pencil (Series IV.), undated (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Scrapbook (Series IV.), 1890s (Box 7, Folder 76)